Guide to "The Landmarks of New York" Photograph Collection 1967-2011 PR 310
New-York Historical Society
The Landmarks of New York photograph collection
1967-2011
New-York Historical Society
PR 310
0.417 Linear feet (1 box)
Photographs of landmarked buildings in New York City from an exhibition curated by Barbaralee Diamonstein-Spielvogel.
Biographical / Historical
'The Landmarks of New York' collection includes over 80 photographs of landmarked buildings in New York that were commissioned for an exhibition to mark the 40th anniversary of New York City Landmarks Preservation Act. The exhibition was sponsored by the U.S. Department of State's Bureau of Educational and Cultural Affairs.
New York City's Landmarks Preservation Act was created in April 1965 in response to the destruction of Pennsylvania Station the previous year to make way for the construction of Madison Square Garden. This act established the New York City Preservation Commission, which is responsible for protecting New York City's architecturally, historically, and culturally significant buildings and sites by granting them landmark or historic district status, and regulating them once they are designated. This Commission is the largest municipal preservation agency in the nation. Since the Landmarks Preservation Act was established in 1965 more than 30,000 structures and environments throughout the five boroughs have been designated as landmarks and thus protected from destruction.
This exhibition, 'The Landmarks of New York', was curated by Barbaralee Diamonstein-Spielvogel. Barbaralee Diamonstein-Spielvogel has devoted her career to preserving New York City's cultural heritage. In 1966, she was appointed the first director of Cultural Affairs for New York City, and went on to become the longest serving Commissioner on the New York City Landmark Preservation Commission (1972 to 1987). She subsequently served as Chair of the Historic Landmarks Preservation Foundation (1987-1995) and since 1995, has been the Chair of the Historic Landmarks Preservation Center.
The photographs in 'The Landmarks of New York' exhibition aim to portray the life and times of an American city from its origins through the colonial and early national periods to its emergence as one of the world largest metropolises. As the city grew, single family houses were replaced by apartment buildings and skyscrapers, and agriculture was replaced by commerce. All of these structures tell the story of New York's journey from a small colonized village to a world class city. The exhibition was created in conjunction with the publication of the book, 'The Landmarks of New York: An Illustrated Record of the City's Historic Buildings', by Barbaralee Diamonstein-Spielvogel.
'The Landmarks of New York' exhibition traveled to 82 countries under the sponsorship of the United States Department of State from 2006 to 2009 and returned home to New York for its final showing. It was exhibited at The New-York Historical Society from April 30 - July 12, 2009. The photographs in the exhibition were then donated to the New-York Historical Society by Barbaralee Diamonstein-Spielvogel, the exhibition's curator.
Scope and Contents
This collection consists of photographs of landmarked buildings from an exhibition at N-YHS that was curated by Barbaralee Diamonstein-Spielvogel. The exhibition featured photographs of a diverse range of landmarked buildings including civic buildings, factories, office towers, bridges, universities, museums, parks, and religious buildings. The photographs were taken between 1967 and 2011; most are exterior shots, although there are also a few landmarked interiors. Collectively, they chronicle the city's architecture from the seventeenth century (the 1652 Pieter Claesen Wyckoff House) to the twentieth century (for example, the Ford Foundation Building begun in 1963). Each of the photographs in 'The Landmarks of New York' was accompanied by historic descriptive text about the landmark and its significance to the cultural heritage of New York. Some notable examples of landmarks in the collection include photographs of Bowne House (1661) in Queens, and in Manhattan, City Hall (1803-12), Chrysler Building (1928-30), Empire State Building (1930-31), Solomon R. Guggenheim Museum and Interior (1956-59), One Chase Manhattan Plaza (1957) and Ford Foundation Building (1963-1967).
Individual buildings are listed in the box and folder list below. Dates listed in the finding aid were taken from the exhibition captions.
Access Restrictions
Available by advance appointment only. To schedule an appointment, contact the Print Room Librarian at printroom@nyhistory.org. Photocopying undertaken by staff only. Limited to twenty exposures of stable, unbound material per day. (Researchers may not accrue unused copy amounts from previous days.)
Provenance
Gift of Barbaralee Diamonstein-Spielvogel, 2009.
- Solomon R. Guggenheim Museum and Interior, 1956-59; addition and renovation, 1989-92; restored 2005-2008 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 1)
- St. Paul's Chapel and Graveyard, 1764-66; porch, 1767-68; tower, 1794 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 1)
- Brooklyn Bridge, c. 1859; 1900s (Offsite-box 1, Folder 1)
- 19th Precinct Station House, 1887 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 1)
- (Former) New York Times Building, 1889-1903 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 1)
- Grand Central Terminal, 1903-13; restored 1994-98; restored 2004-5 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 2)
- The Flatiron Building, 1902; 1991; 2002 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 2)
- Columbia University Low Memorial Library, 1895-97 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 2)
- Four Seasons Restaurant, 1958-59; restored 2009 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 2)
- Carnegie Hall, 1889-1891; addition 1894-96; restored 1986, 2003 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 2)
- The Parachute Jump, 1939; 2003; 2006 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 3)
- One Chase Manhattan Plaza Tower, 1957-1961; plaza 1961-1964 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 3)
- Alice Austen House c 1700; additions c. 1730, 1846, 1852, and 1860-78; 1985 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 3)
- Ridgewood Savings Bank, Forest Hills Branch, 1939-40 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 3)
- Town Hall, 1919-21; 1958 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 3)
- Brown Building (originally Asch Building), 1900-01 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 4)
- TWA Terminal A (formerly Trans World Airlines Flight Center), 1956-62; 2008 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 4)
- Rockefeller Guest House, 1949-50 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 4)
- Jane Hotel, also Hotel Riverview, formerly American Seaman's Friend Society Sailor's Home and Institute, 1907-08 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 4)
- Williamsbridge Reservoir Keeper's House, 1889-90; 1998 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 4)
- Bowne House, 1661; additions 1680, 1691, 1830; restored 2010 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 5)
- Brooklyn Museum, 1895-1915; altered 1934-35; 2004 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 5)
- Steinway Hall, 1924-25 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 5)
- Russell Sage Foundation Building and Annex, 1912-13; penthouse 1922-23; annex 1930-1931 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 5)
- Woolworth Building, 1911-13; 1980s (Offsite-box 1, Folder 5)
- Municipal Building, 1907-14 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 6)
- Louis A. and Laura Stira House, 1908; 1962 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 6)
- Chrystler Building, 1928-30; 1979; 1999 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 6)
- Ritz Tower, 1925-27 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 6)
- Manhattan Bridge Approach, 1906-16 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 6)
- Hearst Magazine Building, 1927-28; 2006 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 7)
- (Former) New York Times Building, 1888-89; enlarged 1903-1905 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 7)
- Hamilton Palace (former Hamilton Theatre), 1912-13 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 7)
- Brooklyn Clay Retort and Fire Brickworks Storehouse, c. 1859; 1990s (Offsite-box 1, Folder 7)
- City Hall, 1803-12; restored, 1954-56; 1956-98; 2003 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 8)
- Statue of Liberty National Monument; design begun, 1871; constructed, 1875-86; restored, 1982-86 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 8)
- Police Building Apartments, 1905-09; 1987 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 8)
- U.S. Custom House, 1907; 1980s (Offsite-box 1, Folder 8)
- Ellis Island, Main Building Interior (also called the Registry Room), 1898-1900; restored, 1986-90 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 8)
- Elizabeth Arden Building (formerly Aeolian Building); designated 2002 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 9)
- New York Stock Exchange Building, 1901-03 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 9)
- Sidewalk Clock 522 Fifth Avenue (Offsite-box 1, Folder 9)
- Bryant Park Hotel (formerly the American Standard Building, originally the American Radiator Building), 1923-24; 2001 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 9)
- 130 West 30th Street, 1927-28; 2003 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 10)
- Joseph Papp Public Theatre/The New York Shakespeare Festival, originally the Astor Library, 1849-53; 1856-59; 1871-81; renovated 1966 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 10)
- Pieter Claesen Wyckoff House, before 1641 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 10)
- Federal Hall National Museum, 1834-42 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 10)
- St. Patrick's Cathedral rectory, 1858-88; archbishop's residence 1882; parish house 1884; Lady Chapel 1900-08 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 10)
- The Plaza Hotel, 1905-07; 1921; 1929; restoration 2005-2008 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 11)
- The Riverside Church, 1928-1930 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 11)
- Mother African Methodist Episcopal Zion Church, 1923-25 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 11)
- J.P. Morgan Chase Bank Building formerly Manufacturers Trust Company Building, 1953-54 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 11)
- Castle Clinton, 1807-11, 1946 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 11)
- Little Red Lighthouse formerly Jeffrey's Hook Lighthouse, 1880; moved to current site and reconstructed 1921 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 12)
- New York Public Library- Main Branch, 1898-1911; renovated 1980s -present (Offsite-box 1, Folder 12)
- Seagram Building, 1956-58 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 12)
- Empire State Building, 1895-98 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 12)
- Harlem River Houses, 1936-37; 1993-94 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 12)
- The Unisphere, 1963-64 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 13)
- Sutton Place Lampost, c. 1913 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 13)
- Promenade and Channel Gardens, 1931-34 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 13)
- New School University auditorium (formerly The New School for Social Research); first Floor Interior 1930-31; restoration, 1992 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 13)
- CBS Building, 1961-64 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 14)
- Begrisch Hall at Bronx Community College, 1956-1961 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 14)
- The Whitehall Building, 1902-1904; extension 1908-1910; 2002 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 14)
- Highbridge-Woodycrest Center formerly American Female Guardian Society and Home for the Friendless, 1901-1902; 1991 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 14)
- New York Life Insurance Company Building ,1926-1927; 1994 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 14)
- Croton Aqueduct West 119th Street Gatehouse, 1894-1895 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 15)
- Puck Building, 1885-86; addition 1892-93; 1899; renovated 1983-84 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 15)
- James Hampden and Cornelia Van Rensselaer Robb House, 1889-92; 1977 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 15)
- Nicholas C. and Agnes Benziger House, 1890-91; 1980; 1989 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 15)
- Charlie Parker Residence, c. 1849; 1990 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 15)
- Bronx Zoological Park (Offsite-box 1, Folder 16)
- Central Park, 1857-present (Offsite-box 1, Folder 16)
- Theodore Roosevelt Birthplace National Historic Site, 1848; reconstructed 1923 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 16)
- Brooklyn Museum (under construction) (Offsite-box 1, Folder 16)
- 240 Central Park South Apartments, 1939-40 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 16)
- Rockefeller Center, 1931-34 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 17)
- The Neil D. Levin Graduate Institute of International Relations and Commerce/SUNY (formerly Teachers Insurance and Annuity Association, originally William and Helen Martin Ziegler, Jr. House), 1926-1927 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 17)
- Park Row Building, 1896-99 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 17)
- Ford Foundation Building, 1963-67 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 17)
- E.V. Haughwout Building, 1857; 1995 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 17)
- Collections file containing further information on each of the landmarks photographed (Offsite-box 1, Folder 17)